[Music]
there are three broad approaches to
mediating the ruin of risky choices
inform people like using labeling nudge
people for example by offering Financial
incentives or directly intervene to make
the activity less harmful which do you
think prevented more car fatalities
mandating driver education labeling cars
about crash risk or removing the human
element alog together by just making
sure airbags are installed there are
public education nutrition campaigns
from sugar pack ads on public transit
informing consumers how much sugar is in
soft drinks to Hot Dogs cause butt
cancer Billboards educating about the
link between processed meat and colorl
cancer but is there a way to make
products nutritionally safe for in the
first place the ban on trans fats offers
a useful lesson in 199 3 the Harvard
nurses study found that high intake of
trans fat may increase the risk of heart
disease by 50% uh that's where the trans
fat story started in Denmark and it
ended a decade later with a ban on added
trans fats there in 2003 it took another
10 years though before the US even
started considering a ban all the while
trans fats were killing estimated tens
of thousands of Americans every year
resulting in his many years of healthy
life loss as conditions like menitis
cervical cancer multiple sclerosis if so
many people were suffering and dying why
did it take so long for the US to even
suggest taking
action one can look at the fight over
New York City's trans fat ban for a
microcosm of the national debate
opposition came down hard from the food
industry complaining about government
intrusion likening the city to a nanny
State since trans fats can be found
naturally in meat and dairy the
livestock industry echoed the Institute
of shortenings everything in moderation
argument critics styled such proposals
as the rise of food
fascism but it was the restaurant and
food industries that limited consumer
Choice by so broadly fouling the food
supply with these dangerous fats if food
zealots get their wish in Banning added
trans fats another argument went what's
next vested corporate interests tend to
Rally around these kinds of slippery
slope arguments to try to distract from
the very real fact that people are dying
I mean what if the government tries to
make us eat
broccoli this actually came up in a
supreme court case over Obamacare chief
justice Roberts suggested Congress could
start ordering everyone to buy
vegetables a fear Justice Ginsburg
dubbed the broccoli horrible technically
Congress could compel the American
public to eat more plant-based Justice
Ginsburg wrote yet one can't offer the
hypothetical and unreal real possibility
of a vegetarian State as a credible
argument as one legal scholar put it
judges and lawyers live on the slippery
slope of analogies they're not supposed
to ski it to the bottom New York City
finally won its trans fat fight
preserving its status as a public health
leader for example New York banned lead
paint 18 years before Federal action was
taken despite Decades of unequivocal
evidence of its harm comparing stroke
and heart attack rates before and after
the rollout of the trans fat ban in
different New York counties researchers
estimated successfully reduced
cardiovascular death rates by about 5%
this then became the model for the
Nationwide ban years later how was the
Public Health Community able to Triumph
when attempts in the past to regulate
the food industry failed if you would
have asked me about the odds of a
national trans fat ban I would have said
fat
chance in Denmark as a leading Danish
cardiologist put it instead of warning
consumers about trans fats and telling
them what they are we've simply removed
them but we're Americans as they say
here you can put poison in the food if
you label it properly if people know the
risk the argument goes then they should
be able to eat whatever they want but
that's assuming they've been given all
the facts which isn't always the case
given the food industry's model of
systemic dishonesty as one Health ethics
Professor put it given the predilection
for predatory deception and manipulation
government intervention was deemed
necessary but how you got kind to get it
past first there was a labeling
requirement manufacturers had to start
adding transact content to products
nutrition facts labeling ostensively
this was to influence consumers but it
may have had a bigger impact on
producers uh now that they had to
divulge the truth companies scrambled to
reformulate their products to gain a no
Transat Competitive Edge within years of
the mandatory disclosure more than 5,000
products were introduced touting low or
zero trans fats on on their labels
Kentucky Fried Chicken went from being
sued for having some of the highest
trans fat levels to running an ad
campaign where mom tells dad in front of
the kids that KFC now has zero grams of
trans fat and the father yells Yeah Baby
Woo and begins eating fried chicken by
the bucket full that was the secret to
passing the ban once the major food
industry players had already
reformulated their products and bragged
about it once there wasn't so much money
at Stig then there was insufficient
political will to block the ban and
added trans Fant were taken off the
playing field
[Music]